



Venketraman Yuvaraj 8056082372 yvenkets@gmail.com https://venketraman.com https://venket.in



Professional Summary

- 11 years of experience in IT industry with experience in Linux, Windows,VMware/Hyper-v/KVM server administration.
- Hands on experience In Cloud Services of AWS, Azure, Rackspace, GCP& O365.
- Hands on experience In DevOps Tools Jenkins, Ansible, Chef, Nagios, Docker, Git.
- Hands on experience in Networking switches and Firewalls.
- Hands on experience in Physical servers, Storage Servers, Rack servers, Hp iLO,Dell IDRAC.
- Hands on experience in Webhosting ,DNS Management and migrate the servers to cloud.

Tools & Technologies

Cloud Technologies - AWS, Azure, Rackspace, O365

Operating systems - Red hat 6, Cent OS 7, Ubuntu, Microsoft Servers 2003, 2008 R2, 2012 R2, 2016.

Hardware - HP Blade Server, HP Proliant Servers and Dell PowerEdge Servers.

Database - My SQL ,MongoDB,MS SQL

Web Hosting - LMS,CMS,LAMP,IIS,Tomcat,Nginx

Domain Management - Godaddy,Route 53,Hostinger,Cloudflare.

Monitoring Tools - Nagios, Cloudwatch, Op-manager, Spice works ,DellKace

Virtualization - VMware 6.0, KVM ,Hyper-V

Security - Fortinet (300C, 60D), Sophos XG 135
Endpoint - Sophos Endpoint Protection, Mcafee

Version Control - Git,SVN,TFS

Professional Experience

Blue Marble Smart Ware Pvt Ltd., Chennai

06/2016 - Present

Designation: Systems Administrator

Responsibilities: Manage In-house Physical and virtual server, AWS / Azure cloud server & services, domain management , webhosting, monitirong, patch update, deploy servers and services on servers, vms and docker containers.

Cloud

Launching and configuring of Amazon EC2 Instances and Azure VMs.

- Experience In AWS services EC2,S3,Lamda,VPC,Route53,Cloudwatch,Loadbalancer,auto scaling,IAM,Billing,AWS Cli.
- Experience in the AWS Devops services like Codecommit,code Build,Code deploy,Code Pipeline
- Designed and configure the application server using load balancer and EC2
- Worked as a part of AWS build team on AWS Single Sign On, AWS VPN Connection, Custom VPC and Migrating and Managing DNS entries in Route 53.
- Provisioning RDS database Servers for PHP and other applications servers.
- Configuring Cloud Watch alerts and for monitoring Instance, RDS, ELB, EBS and S3.
- Knowledge in creating and configuring S3 bucket with restricted policies, Lifecycle Management,
 Versioning and Amazon Glacier for archiving data
- Launching and configuring of Amazon EC2 Instances using AMI's and configuring the servers for specified applications.
- Creating AMI images of critical ec2 instances as backup and will do AMI's windows hardening.
- Having the experince in aws services Code commit, Cloud trail, Storage gateway, EFS
- Create the users, roles, policies and provide rights to users in IAM
- Experienced in Amazon certificate manager.
- Designing and Deploying Highly scalable infrastructure using AWS EC2, Auto Scaling, Elastic Load Balancer, VPC, IAM, Cloud Watch, RDS, S3 and Route 53 services.
- Implemented and managing Nagios monitoring tool in AWS.
- Monitoring and alerting on physical servers, VM's and aws Instances using Nagios and Cloudwatch.

Migration

- Migrating AWS to on premise VM's using AWS Import/Export.
- Migrating on premise VM's to Azuere using Azure Site Recovery.
- Migrating on premise VM's to AWS with AWS server migration services.
- Host and Migrate the webservers from NYI to Azure, Azure to in-house Datacenter.
- Dockerize the Physical server to a Docker container.
- Convert Physical machine as VMs and migrate to AWS And Azure cloud infra

Server Administration

- Expertise in installing and configuring a virtual machine in Hyper-V , KVM and VMware.
- Installing, configuring & administrating File servers in windows server 2012 R2 & windows 2016
- Monitoring and Managing IT environment which includes physical, virtual and cloud servers.
- Managed windows services AD, DNS, DHCP, TFS, IIS, Group policy, WSUS, WDS.
- Involve and supporting in all operations in Datacenter, like in Day-to-day activities and during
 maintenance and emergency time. Need to review the Active Directory policies, manage users, computer,
 groups and OUs as per ISMS needs.
- Configure and managed Sophos XG firewall (VPN,NATing,Web filter rules,Port forwarding,LDAP Auth)
- Implement the Open source video conferencing Server using Jitsi
- Implement the Online learning Management servers(LMS) Moodle, BigBlueButton.
- Implement the Online Stremaning Server service Ant Media server.
- Configure Multi sites on nginx, Apache and IIS
- Configure Reverse proxy, Loadbalancer, Multisite on Nginx server for Node Application servers.
- Implement the Gitlab CE Server in on premises data center to secure the application source code.

Client Projects:

Client: Abaxystech (Devops Project)

- Implement Openvpn for secure the network
- Implement The CI/CD Pipe line with high availabity DevOps Architecture on AWS Servers
- To integrate the pipeline install and configure Jenkins
- To Isolate the network using cutom VPC and private Subnet implementation
- To secure the source code using code commit
- Implemet Apache virtual host for Cost Efficency in Development environment
- Using lambda function schedule the servesr uptime and down time.

Client: Mobile MediClaim - (AWS Dev ops Project)

- Implement The DEvops CiCD Pipeleine using aws Devops tools (Codecommit,code Build,Code deploy,Code Pipeline)
- To deploy the Java application configure the Docker service in AWS Ec2 servers.
- Implement application load balancer for isolate the product server

Client: SCEH (Dr. Shroff's Charity Eye Hospital) (AWS Web Server)

- Implement Wordpress CMS server for Client website
- Install configure the Product server using IIS with dotnet core application on AWS
- Implemet the loadbalncer for product Servers high availability
- Using cloudflare for secure website from DDos Attacks

S4Carlisle Publishing Services, Chennai

07/2011 - 05/2016

Designation: Systems Engineer (L2)

- Building, Installation, configuration and administration of Windows 2012/2008/2003 servers and Linux Cent OS for applications hosting.
- Build and Configure Sharepoint Server 2013 with SQL Server 3 tier architecture.
- Maintenance and Monitoring of Servers like HP EVA (HP Proliant DL 380 Gp), HP Blade server bl 460c and Dell power edge 1950 servers.
- Managed windows services AD, DNS, DHCP, TFS, IIS, Group policy, Terminal Services
- Installed, configured and managed WSUS service in server 2012 for Windows patch management.
- Building and configure Open fire Instant Messaging Server integrate with MySQL Database in CentOS/Server2012 for internal and external communication.
- Managed Nagios Server for Monitoring
- Managed Postfix Mail Server
- Maintained Mcafee Endpoint Protection Server
- Active Directory Services Managing Users & Other Resource objects.

- Managed Exchange 2010 / 0365 in Mailbox creation, distribution group creation, Mail Contact.
- Maintained Sophos Endpoint Protection Server (Updating the Virus Definition, creating the package, configuring Group Policy and also configuring the Client Exception scanning & Generating Reports).
- Having Knowledge in Fortigate 300C & 60D Firewalls, VPN User Creation, Web filter.
- Configured FTP Servers and Webservers (LAMP Server) in Cent OS.
- Monitored the server health and performance with performance monitor tool OpManager.
- Provided Technical support for US clients through MX Meeting, Team Viewer and Dame ware

Wonder Soft Technologies, Chennai

03/2011 - 06/2011

Designation: Technical Support Engineer

- Deployed OS through WDS
- Hardware and Software Asset, License compliance Management through Dell KACE
- Troubleshoot basic level system issues
- Provided Application Support for remote customer over Phone and team viewer.
- Configured VOIP phones (Zultys VOIP), Web conference through MX Meeting.
- Vendor Co-ordination in purchase, logging calls and ensuring getting spare parts replaced.

Certifications

- AWS Certified Solutions Architect Associate (2018) (Validation Number: PDDE5QD2BMFEQ2SV)
- Red Hat Certified System Administrator (2012) (Certification ID : 120-205-455)
- Diploma in Hardware and Networking (2007): NIT Trichy

Educations

Master of Computer Applications, Thiruvalluvar University, Vellore. (2007-2010)

Language Known: English and Tamil

Date :

Place : Chennai (Y. Venketraman)